I think everyone's fine with that.
And we're just going to start the hearing of evidence.
We've got ECPAT New Zealand, Eleanor Parks.
So Eleanor Parks, if you're on, we will hear from you
for 10 minutes.
Kia ora. Thank you. Can you hear me?
Welcome. We've got 10 minutes with you today.
We'll probably have some questions, so if you could probably just leave a couple of
minutes near the end, and if we're nearing maybe nine minutes or
so, and you're still talking away there, I'll just give you an indication you've
got a couple of minutes to go. But welcome.
Thank you. Yeah, let me know how we go for time.
I would like to allow time for questions if you have them.
I'm assuming everyone's read the written submission, so I'll try not to repeat too
much of it. For people who haven't met me before, I'm Eleanor Parks
from ECPAT New Zealand. We've obviously been watching very closely
since late 2025, when Section 17 was
suspended under urgency. Overseas adoptions are
very much in our wheelhouse. We're an anti-trafficking organization,
and so cases like Matamata and more recently the Tuai
case have demonstrated how these informal pathways really can be
weaponized for modern slavery. So we're very supportive of the fact that
the government is looking into address these loopholes and
do something about them.
For a bit of background, part of ECPAT International, so the largest
network of organizations working to end child sexual
exploitation and trafficking. That is the specific focus.
And our work in New Zealand is very much grounded in research,
advocacy, and lived experience of young people here and
frontline workers like social workers here.
We've consistently focused on safeguarding children from
exploitation and domestic trafficking and international trafficking.
So that includes things like the misuse of adoption practices.
What we do know is that while cases of child trafficking in New
Zealand rarely make headlines, there are also the many, many stories of
successful, life-changing cross-border support for children,
stories where children have been provided with safety and family and
opportunity, that don't make headlines.
And so our challenge and your challenge is to stop the abuse,
the cases of abuse and exploitation, but without stopping those
good, positive cases that are giving these children what they really
need to be safe and to thrive. And at the moment, this
bill, while very well intended, isn't quite hitting that mark.
So I'd like to go into a few details around some of our concerns.
So we definitely are supporting strong protections.
We want to prevent child trafficking, and we want to stop overseas
adoption processes from being misused.
And we want effective scrutiny where there are child
protection concerns.
But at the moment, the framework in its current form would likely
unintentionally deny certain children access to care,
family support, education, health services, and
stable living arrangements
if they do not come from a country that has yet been designated
under a future regulatory process.
So
looking at Section 17 just as a trafficking loophole
misreads a pathway that has also enabled
legitimate Pacific kinship care based in cross-border
family support, and these are the children that we're concerned will be missing
out on that safety and security.
A few details on that. On the
surface, the provisions definitely look to reduce the risk of
adoption being used inappropriately for
immigration or exploitation,
but it doesn't make a distinction between adoptions that are
undertaken to secure those immigration outcomes and facilitate
abuse and adoption that is being used as the
genuine kinship care arrangements that are in the best
interests of the child.
In a Western view, adoption is seen as a solution
for a child with no family or no suitable family,
and Western adoption laws, including the Hague Convention, which has been a big
part of this conversation, are built on that clean break
idea. The child is removed from unsuitable parents and transplanted to
better ones. But in the Pacific, adoption is
often additive.
We're not replacing children's parents with better ones.
It's about gaining additional caregivers.
At the moment, the proposed amendments really impose that
Western nuclear family model
in places that don't necessarily fit, that don't align with
Pacific ways of understanding family.
In the Pacific, these kinds of care, this kinship customary care, is
recognized and it's a valued practice, with children moving between households and
communities and countries within their family
networks. And it's not about
circumventing immigration rules.
It's about welfare, it's about education, it's about support.
And this applies to a lot of children in New Zealand.
It's estimated that 3.2% or as much as
5% of all children in New Zealand are
living in kinship care arrangements outside of
formal statutory care.
Kinship care isn't a risk factor, it's a protective
asset.
We want to be careful not to be removing the protective
aspect.
What we need is to reconcile
The best interests of the child as the primary
consideration,
and it's just not quite happening yet.
So any legislative framework governing overseas adoptions,
they do need to be measured against our obligations
under the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child.
So that includes the best interests of the child, preservation of family
relationships, which covers the importance of family
relationships, identity, and appropriate alternative care.
It says that legislation should avoid unnecessarily disrupting family-based
care arrangements where safeguards can be demonstrated.
And it also covers protection from exploitation, of course.
But those safeguards need to be targeted at identifying the risk where it actually
exists, which is very often at the level of the individual
caring arrangement in the receiving country.
So
not only focusing on where the children are coming from, but focusing
on what are the child protection
arrangements here in New Zealand when those children are here.
We can't just be monitoring what is happening in the sending
countries if the abuse is happening here, which is what we've seen.
Eleanor, we've got a couple of minutes still with you, but I have got a question
from Dan Rosewarne. I'm wondering, do you want to take that question and then come
back to a summary from you?
Yeah, absolutely. Let's do that.
Dan, thank you.
Yeah, thanks Chair, and thanks Eleanor for your submission.
You've kind of traversed the culturally grounded kinship care
arrangements such, like the Pacific community in particular.
I was just wondering how you would like to see that reflected in the
legislation. Are you thinking like a definition of exceptional
circumstances, or a list of examples, or like a separate
provision dealing specifically with kinship care
arrangements?
Yeah. Great question, because it does say it refers
to exceptional circumstances
within the current wording, but it doesn't define
what those might include. So we would suggest just to
avoid that sort of arbitrary or inconsistent interpretation
of that, this bill should explicitly recognize culturally grounded
kinship care arrangements, such as those common in Pacific
communities, as qualifying exceptional circumstance.
That would be our preference. That would be the strongest way to do it.
If the
committee is not
of a mind to include it within this legislation and they would like to-- There are
ways of doing it outside of this legislation as a separate
pathway because, like we said, this isn't a classic
Western-style adoption. It doesn't have to fit here.
But we would be very concerned if this piece of legislation was
to be progressed and the committee just thought, "Well, someone
else can deal with that later because it needs to sit elsewhere." That needs to be
happening alongside, and really this process needs to
be slowed down
to allow for that if it is going to happen outside of this legislation.
Otherwise, we're concerned it just would not be the priority,
and it would never happen. We would effectively have
this in place for the longer term without those other
additional factors.
Thanks, Eleanor. That's helpful.
We've got about just about a minute or so left, Eleanor, if you'd just like to
just do a summary and
go from there.
Yeah. I think
really we've covered everything.
We need to be able to distinguish within any
legislation between harmful arrangements and protective ones,
and
a child-centered system should be capable of making that distinction.
So it needs a bit more nuance in that way.
We're not going to find effective safeguards in black and
white impermeable barriers. We need some carefully designed
pathways that really do identify risk and monitor
welfare and preserve children's rights to family and culture and identity
and belonging, and with that comes safety and security and a
chance for those children to thrive.
We
don't need to deny those opportunities to keep them safe
from exploitation if we can add some nuance and be a little more
thorough in our approach to this.
That's fantastic, Eleanor. Thank you very much for your submission today, and
thank you again. Our next submitter today is Max Marshall.
I think you may be in person in the room or otherwise
online, but we'll just wait for Max.
He's online, Mr. Chair. Just bringing him in now.
Fantastic.
Are you there, Max, or are we still waiting?
I'm here. Hi.
G'day, Max. Welcome to your submission today.
We've got five minutes with you, so if you'd like to leave some time,
I'll indicate when you've got about a minute to go. So, we're in your hands.
Okay. Good stuff. Thanks.
Good morning, and
thank you for giving me an opportunity to speak to
you. I want to
speak in support of
many of the other submitters who have
spoken today.
History has shown that
many of these
overseas adoptions have had bad
outcomes, and I want to protect the welfare of the child.
There have been situations in which we've created a problem for a child.
As for any child, no one is born with a
tabula rasa. The circumstances of
one's background provides challenges particular to
it. For the case of the adoptee, the circumstances of
adoption start off with
complications, and these have been well documented,
as there is a need to protect the child's welfare in the
process.
I want to talk about how this
relationship is unique. What I mean by unique is that
it is an option beyond more accessible options
of local adoptions that we are choosing over.
I do not subscribe to the notion of overseas
adoption wholly subscribing to the needs of the parents.
I want to talk against the commodification of desire.
A Soviet pilot who lands on American soil seeking asylum
does not make him automatically an American citizen who has grown
up all their life in that society.
The same A is not going to be.
In our instant age, we demand our needs be met,
be gratified instantly,
and the children's needs are often lost in the frame of the
parent's
powerful desire for an ideal family.
What is testimony to an ideal family is a
powerful motivation
lies inside
is this desire to have a family.
Inside monarchs, the vision promoted
by
a particular monarch was to be seen with other
powerful monarchs to project this vision of power to his subjects.
King Richard the Lionheart and King Philip of France having a
sleepover would be the equivalent version to the
contemporary one, a jaunty spread in a Hello!
Magazine.
It does not carry the same private or romantic meaning as it does
today. And it is uncomfortable to reflect on
its behavior then, but I am uncomfortable in the same way about
overseas adoption,
about how it does not configure to
this deeper cultural idea about home and
family.
I argue that inside these projects, the welfare of
the child is hidden by the projects of that-
Just over a minute now, Max. So you just-
So this must stand as an anathema to what the concept of family
means in terms of formation, love, and
belonging. I'm not hostile to the project of
overseas adoption, but I am aware that lawmakers
must put in place safeguards which recognize the welfare of the
child as its primary aim.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Max. I'm not seeing any
questions. Is there any questions, members?
No, I'm not seeing any. So thank you very much, Max, for your time today and
for your submission.
Thank you. Our next submitter is the New Zealand Law
Society, so we'll just wait a moment for them to come online.
Welcome. Welcome, Margaret Casey KC.
Nice to see you today. I think we may be also getting joined by another
one of your colleagues, if that's right.
Lena, yes.
Yep. I'm not seeing her at the moment, but-- Oh,
no, we have got her now.
So welcome. We have got 10 minutes of your time today.
Please leave some time for some questions.
If
we're still going around about eight minutes, I'll just let you know, just so you
know where your timing is. So welcome.
Thank you.
Kia ora koutou katoa. Good morning from
Tāmaki Makaurau. And you have two of us
here today to speak to the New Zealand Law Society
submission that we filed. We are conscious that it is a lengthy
submission,
but there's a reason for that.
This is a very discreet area of law.
There are very few lawyers in the country that actually work in the
adoption area, and even less who work in the field of
surrogacy and international surrogacy.
So we've approached the bill very much as the people
best to stress test it.
What is it going to work? How is it going to work in practice?
For
myself, I bring to the group
over 20 years work in the area of adoption
and surrogacy. I'm very involved in the
international work about cross-border surrogacy arrangements,
having spent 10 years working on a Hague project
where they were trying to establish cross-border surrogacy.
I say that just to explain the reason why we have put in
examples so that you know that these are real-world examples that we
have used to highlight some of the issues that we have
identified with the bill.
Having said all of that,
we're very comfortable with the bill as a way of trying to
protect children from trafficking and exploitation.
Our concern has been, and you'll see that highlighted again and again in the
submission, is that unintentionally this bill may
expose another group of children to different risks, legal
limbo, insecure or no parentage,
unequal treatment, and in some case, statelessness.
And we believe that the bill can work for both groups of people, and we shouldn't
be having to choose between the different cohorts of
children. And that is
the
focus we have brought to our submissions.
We wanted to address two or three particular points, and
primarily they are focused at the
Family Court jurisdiction and wanting to preserve that because
we, in the field, believe the Family Court is doing
a very good job
at doing what it needs to do to protect children.
Remembering that some of these recognition cases don't actually
come before the Family Court.
They are not the issue that we
see in terms of what we've identified.
So Selina is going to just talk to you about some of the restrictions on the Family
Court jurisdiction by reference to our submission.
Thank you.
Tena koutou. Good morning. As Margaret has just said, I will be
addressing the committee regarding the bill's limitations on the
Family Court's jurisdiction. And the society's concerns around this
limitation are twofold. The bill introduces
barriers that firstly prevent the Family Court from recognizing
genuine parent-child relationships, even where that's in the child's
interest to do so. And secondly, it creates a
barrier to the court carrying out its very important protective
function.
In cases where there is not an international surrogacy or where the
parties and child are not all ordinarily resident to New Zealand,
the bill really narrows access to the court's expertise by imposing
this very high three-pronged cumulative threshold.
And it goes even further because the bill also creates situations where there's no
pathway to the court at all, where both the child and the adoptive
parents are living overseas.
And we consider that these jurisdictional restrictions in the bill are really
inconsistent with the fundamentally child-centered
approach that should underpin all adoption decisions, indeed all
decisions affecting children, in line with the United Nations
Convention on the Rights of the Child.
We think it's really important to remember that our Family Court has spent more
than 70 years determining adoption applications through
a child-centered process that's really focused on the welfare and the
best interests of the child. Throughout that time, the court
has evolved, and it's been really nimble in interpreting the
legislation to meet the changing social needs of the
families that come before it.
The court is undertaking the very inquiries and
tests that Parliament is concerned are not happening in non-designated
countries, and it's uniquely equipped to identify
unsafe arrangements, assess consent, scrutinize the
evidence, and where necessary, refuse inappropriate
applications.
As I mentioned earlier, some children will be excluded from the court's
consideration altogether, not because the adoption is
unsafe, but because that statutory gateway is just simply too
restrictive. And the consequence will be that some children of New
Zealanders may be unable to secure legal recognition
of the parent-child relationship, even when that's plainly in that child's
best interest. And that's likely to create adverse
situations where some children face very different outcomes from their
siblings solely because they were adopted rather than being born
into the family. And at paragraph 4.15 of our
submission, we outline two real-life
examples of where that would happen.
So it's this society's submission that there needs to remain a pathway
for the courts to consider such cases, again, particularly where
doing so will promote the welfare of the child.
Ultimately, it's our view that the child bears the consequences of this bill.
Children don't choose the circumstances of their birth, they don't choose where
they are born and where they live, and they certainly do not choose the legal
arrangements made by adults. But under this bill,
some of those children will be left without appropriate legal recognition of their
parentage and the consequences that come with that.
The consequences being denial to that child of legal recognition
of their parentage, denial of security of status,
denial of inheritance rights, and denial of a really clear
pathway to citizenship and united family life.
Our submission isn't that safeguards should be weakened.
It is that when you limit the jurisdictional access to the court, a really
important safeguard is being diminished.
The court remains a strong guard against trafficking, coercion, and
exploitation. And further, by limiting the court's jurisdiction, you're
creating this pendulum swing that creates other risks for children
because, as we've said, some children will lose the meaningful ability
to come before the court and have the court consider their individual
case on their merits in order to avoid unintended
consequences.
Paragraph 4.24 of our submission summarizes our
recommendations for mitigating these risks and
these concerns, and those proposed
amendments are really aimed at achieving the
necessary balance. As Margaret said earlier, we don't need to choose
between different risks here or different categories of
children. We can achieve a balance.
I'll now just hand over to Margaret to address you on, I believe,
international surrogacy arrangements.
We've got a couple of minutes left, Margaret.
We may still also have a question, so I'm kind of just in your
hands. Yeah.
Okay. I will be snappy.
Thank you.
Lawyers can actually do that. What I want to just draw to the attention is
that the submission at 5.5, again, it's just another narrowing of
the jurisdictional gateway, and it's this gnarly issue
around what do we do with the international surrogacy arrangements where
parents come to New Zealand where there's less than optimal practices
have been observed. Currently, the bill basically
prevents those from having the parentage established
through an adoption order, and our submission is
that of course we want to discourage those practices.
But again, we are punishing the wrong people by preventing those
children from having status recognition,
stable legal parentage, and often statelessness avoided.
We would remove that limitation. The court is getting
practice at dealing with the critical analysis and
intense scrutiny required in some of these emerging
cases, but two points about that. The number of
illegal practice surrogacies coming to the court at the moment
is still very low compared to the large number of people who
actually do things right.
And as a society, my second point is, as a society, we
have embraced surrogacy as a means of creating a
family. So it is -- we should be providing a mechanism
for parentage. And if we could bring the changes to
this alongside with the surrogacy reform
practices,
the new surrogacy reform bill, we might see less people traveling
overseas and more focusing on domestic surrogacy arrangements,
so thereby reducing those illegal practice international
surrogacy cases.
We've got two questions for you, so we'll go quickly. Dan and then Camilla.
So Dan, please.
Thanks, Chair. Hey, you raised concerns in paragraph
2.7 about Section 19 of the Bill of
Rights Act, and I was just wondering, in your view, what alternative
approaches are there that would still protect children from
trafficking and exploitation and avoid the discriminatory
effect on children adopted overseas and their families?
The reason I ask is because your submission appears to suggest that there may be
other ways of achieving the bill's child protection objectives
without creating the same impact on overseas adopted
children and their families. I just want to understand what we as a
committee should be weighing up in that space.
Selena.
I think the rest of our submissions
are aimed at doing that, at achieving that balance between protecting
children from the harms and actually ensuring that we don't then
swing the pendulum too far the other way.
So we've got a number of
recommendations throughout the submission that
are aimed at exactly doing that, and in doing so,
avoid some of the discriminatory aspects.
One of the key discriminatory aspects from our perspective is the limitations
on visas and citizenship, where you create a subclass of
children who, by virtue of being adopted, are suddenly
denied the very citizenship that they would have had, had they been
born to that family. So, that is a very key area which we
see as needing to be addressed. Yeah.
Thank you. That's helpful.
Camilla.
Thanks. And can I just say thank you very much, and to the entire
committee that worked on this for such extensive submission in an area that you're
obviously really expert in. So thank you very much for that.
I just had a quick follow-up on the Bill of Rights, but my--
Which is, I think I noted that you said that you thought it was defective, and we
can obviously raise that with officials.
But the kind of natural conclusion of that is that, is there likely to
be a breach that
you think is evident that hasn't been picked up by
the vet?
But the main issue that I
wanted to ask you about is you raised the surrogacy
bill, which is currently going through Parliament, and I just wanted to ask
you how,
how important is it that that bill
is linked with this bill? Is it possible for--
I'm just kind of wanting to get a flavor of whether progressing this bill
is going to impact on that bill if it's
done totally separately as it is proposed at the moment, or whether there needs to
be a stronger kind of linkage between the two,
because obviously, and especially in relation to surrogacy, they're
so interconnected.
Shall I take that one, Selena?
Yeah, by all means.
They are interconnected. They're interconnected this way, that our
current surrogacy practice is that we
establish the new parentage, the intended parentage, through the
adoptive pathway, and we do that for domestic
surrogacies and international surrogacies.
The proposed bill would remove adoption
as the mechanism for transferring parentage.
Domestic adoptions would not come anywhere near a court if they'd gone through an
ethical approved pathway. International surrogacy arrangements
would still have to go to court and apply for a parentage
order. So if we'd--
The provisions around the international surrogacy arrangements, however they are
addressed in this legislation, need to synchronize
with the pattern that we've provided for the new pathway in
that.
The other aspect in the surrogacy reform bill is that it allows
for recognition of foreign judgments where-
Parentage has been established following surrogacies, and
so there's a provision that deals with Section 17.
Now, this
adoption
amendment started life because of the concerns around Section 17,
and the surrogacy reform has a very
beautifully drafted
provision in there to enable recognition of
parentage that has been established by a foreign judgment in a
surrogacy case, in the kind of countries that we're happy to work
with. So again, that does need to be woven together
so we don't just create work for us all as we're trying to
put these all into place.
I'm just going to jump in there. Thank you very much, Margaret, for your time.
We went a little bit over, but those questions were very valuable.
So thank you very much to the Law Society.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you. Hey, Liam, are you online there?
Do we have this other submitter? We've got a late submitter in Mr.
Kenrick. Is that person online
wanting to make a submission?
Sorry, that was a late written submission request.
Is it only written? Okay. Yeah. So is the committee happy to accept that late
submission? I can't see any reason not to.
Okay. We're in agreement to accept that.
And we are two minutes away, I believe, from
starting our move on orders. So if anyone
wants to take a minute or 90 seconds before we start those
hearings.
The only other thing was, do we need to instruct a
departmental report? The committee might
want to wait to go to private session to do that, Mr. Chair. Okay.
So do we do that now, Liam? Do we go- The first submitter we have up is Paul
McMahon. Okay. Would you like to move him? Yep. Paul McMahon.
So we'll just wait for Paul, also for
a five-minute submission.
Hello, can you hear me?
Good day, Paul. Welcome to the Justice Committee.
You're actually our first submitter on this bill, so it's Summary Offences and
move on orders. We've got five minutes with you today, and we look forward to what
you've got to say. If you want to leave a minute or two at the end
for questions, otherwise I'll give you a prompt maybe with about 30 seconds to go.
Okay. Thank you, Mr. Chair, and thank you to the committee for the opportunity to
speak.
My name's Paul McMahon. I'm submitting as an individual, and I want to make one
central point today as plainly as I can that this bill is
unnecessary.
Let me start with why it isn't needed.
Everything genuinely harmful that this bill is aimed
at is already against the law.
If someone is threatening people, that's already an offense.
If they're intimidating shoppers, obstructing a doorway, fighting,
breaching the peace, the Summary Offences Act already covers it.
Today,
Summary Offences Act already covers it, and
today, the police have already have the Power
Act. They can direct people to move on.
They can arrest.
Those tools exist, and they are already used.
So the honest question for this committee is not do we want safer
streets? Of course we do. It's what does this bill
add that the law doesn't already provide?
And the answer is that the only thing it adds is the power over conduct that
is not otherwise a crime. Asking a stranger for
help and sleeping when you have nowhere else to go.
Now, I could sit here and simply assert that, but I don't need to
because the people who said it first
already work for the government.
The police advise that existing tools are already sufficient,
and that law enforcement is not an effective way to deal with homelessness or
poverty.
The agency that would have to operate this power told the ministers it doesn't need
it.
The Ministry of Justice, in its regulatory impact statement, went further
and said, and I'm quoting, "Move on orders may merely
displace behavior rather than addressing or resolving it." It said
the harm from passive behavior like this is negligible, and that
acting against it is likely to be an unjustified intrusion
into people's rights.
It preferred the status quo because the costs outweigh the
benefits. And the attorney general, the
senior minister in this government, reported that the begging and rough sleeping
provisions are inconsistent with the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act
and unjustifiably limit freedom of movement and freedom of
expression.
So consider where that leaves us. The police say it isn't needed.
The Ministry of Justice says it won't work and shouldn't be done.
The attorney general says it breaches our bill of rights.
When a government has to override its own police, its own officials, and its own
law officer to pass a bill,
that is usually a sign that a bill should not pass.
This is not a close call about a gap in the law.
It is a new coercive power resting on one officer's
discretion with no oversight and no appeal, applying to
children as young as 14, and is being created to do a job that the
existing law already does,
or that the experts say it cannot do at all.
That is the definition of unnecessary legislation.
I'd ask this committee to be conservative about power in the proper
sense. Don't create a power the state doesn't need.
We've got a question from Dan Rosewarne
Hey, thanks, Paul
I hadn't quite finished.
Oh.
That's all right.
If I've still got time, Mr. Chair?
Yeah. We're just getting short. We've got about a minute, so if you want to
I'm happy to take a question from Mr. O'Connor.
Take a question. Thank you.
Thanks, Paul. In your submission, you describe a period when
Morston residents and businesses had genuine concerns about
safety. But you also say those issues were dealt with without
any additional move on powers. I was just wondering if you could tell the
committee what worked in practice, and what lessons we should
take from that experience when we're considering this bill?
Yeah. Well, very briefly, one thing is we had an
alcohol ban put in place, which is available under
the current law.
And we also managed to get alcohol retailers to
stop selling particular products in the area.
And we worked with government agencies in order
to provide the support that was necessary to those people.
And the police played their part in enforcing the alcohol ban, but
also just
having a presence in the area where perhaps they hadn't been as
focused.
And actually getting people help was the key.
And as I said in my written submission, there's two real groups
of people, and the people who are the hardest up,
the rough sleepers, they actually just need support.
And most of the time, their behavior is
pretty good because they realize that they are surviving on the
support of the community. And there is another group of people
who really did need to be moved on, but their behavior meant
that they could be anyway. And there's no
additional powers needed coercive.
In fact, what you're going to end up is having
people think that they've solved the problem, when really you're just going to
be ultimately punishing the people who are in the most difficult
position in their lives in our society.
Thanks, Paul. Going to thank you very much, Paul, for your submission today.
We're running out of time there, but thank you again.
Our next submitter is,
I think it's Áine Kelly-Costello.
We'll just wait for her to come online.
Kia ora, can you hear me?
Oh, yes, we can. Thank you. Hello. Welcome to the Justice Committee.
We have five minutes with you today. We're in your hands now.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Thank you.
So my name is Áine.
I'm a disabled person
who's very embedded within disability community in my advocacy and
research.
I am not an expert on this bill, but I
know people for whom it would apply and would likely apply,
and so I want to
add my voice to oppose the bill,
and recommend that it do not proceed in any form.
So I would consider that move on orders,
particularly in the case of people who
are most at risk and who have been at the receiving end
of poverty and structural harm, is not
only a false solution, but also one that is
actively harmful and conflates homelessness with
criminality.
So we know that homelessness
largely results from structural conditions,
caused broadly by the failure of successive governments,
and particularly this government,
to meaningfully move us towards equitable wealth distribution and
investments in affordable public goods like public
housing.
And we also know that disabled people have disproportionately high
rates of homelessness, and particularly for Maori and
Pacific and Rainbow communities,
as well as women fleeing violence.
Another group who are very impacted by this,
of which disabled people are also over-represented, is survivors of
abuse in institutions,
including government care, in
quotation marks,
as well as institutions managed outside
of direct government control. And so the state sort
of having the power to ask people to
move along without actually
providing any meaningfully helpful kind of intervention
may be re-traumatizing as well.
I also think that this
bill may lead to a degree of disability
profiling or disability related targeting, or disabled people being
stigmatized or suspect just for talking or
moving or acting in a certain way, which is
only because they are disabled.
And we also know that most of our homeless whanau
are Maori or Pacific, so this bill also
punches down and punishes those at the end of
colonial and racialized structural harm and disadvantage.
So you'll hear from many with much more firsthand
expertise and experience in relation to this bill.
But as the previous submitter said, when the government's own
agencies are saying this bill is not a good idea and should not proceed,
I think that should be a very strong sign.
And all I can say is, I want to live in a Motuora where
we actually care about people, particularly people who have the least,
and where government is then genuinely committed to
structural solutions that help rather than being
punitive and harmful band-aids. Kia ora.
Thank you very much. We have a question from Camilla Belich.
Thank you very much for your detailed and articulate submission.
I just had a question around, I think, a very good point that you raise on the
impact of these move on orders on disabled communities.
We have had some concerns raised with us around
people who have unmet mental health needs.
But just wanting to understand your submission, would your submission be that
it would be people who have unmet mental health needs or disabilities,
perhaps in relation to mental health, but additionally those with physical
disabilities who may be unfairly targeted by move on orders?
Thank you for the question. Yeah, and I think
because a lot of our lives as disabled people
are comparatively precarious
because of not having housing that's meeting our needs or of
economic conditions, there can be a really big overlap.
There can be a lot of people who have multiple disabilities.
We have statistics that show that there's unmet
mental health services need within disability community that's
disproportionately high for our community as well.
So, yeah, big overlaps.
We've got no further questions, but just thank you very much for your
time and the clarity around your submission today. So, thank you.
Thank you.
We're now going to head to, and we're just moving around members a little bit.
We're going to the Public Housing Futures, Vanessa
Cole. Just wait till Vanessa's online.
Kia ora.
Hi, Vanessa. Welcome. We've got 10 minutes with you today.
So if you want to go into your main points for your submission, and
please leave some time for questions.
Kia ora koutou.
Thank you for the opportunity to submit today.
My name's Vanessa Cole, tangata Tiriti.
I'm based in Tāmaki Makaurau, and I'm a
campaigner at ActionStation Aotearoa, but working on the Public Housing
Futures campaign.
I guess I want to start by saying most days on my way
to mahi, I walk past the train station
in New Lynn and past one of the 213
canceled state housing developments, which would have provided 80
decent and stable units for people in our community.
It is now being sold on the private market, alongside many
other developments that have been canceled across the country.
And right across from this canceled
state housing development that would've provided homes for people in our community,
is our local community center, where homeless whanau
sleep outside at night, sheltered in the doorway.
We should be passing legislation at the moment that takes really
serious the housing crisis and moves people from the
streets, from their cars, into permanent and
stable housing.
Not legislation that displaces homeless whanau and put them at
risk of being criminalized and imprisoned for not having
access to housing. These move on
orders have come at a time where the government has made political
choices, which has led to an increase in homelessness.
They have changed the criteria to access emergency
housing, putting up barriers that really
put the blame on people for a housing crisis that they have no part
in creating. And as we've all kind
of been exposed to recently, putting directives to MSD staff,
which has led to KPIs that deny people access to
emergency housing.
Now, we all know that emergency housing was never the answer.
Permanent housing is.
But this massive increase in homelessness that we have seen,
and that many frontline community organizations and local councils have
recorded, is directly connected to these decisions
that have led to people being denied access to immediate
shelter.
And this is not really even counting the over 100,000
people who were homeless in this country at the time of the last census, who
might not necessarily be visible or connected to local organizations,
sleeping on couches and cars and in garages.
The government made a political decision to stop the construction of
3,500 new Kainga Ora homes across the country.
Sections are sitting empty, and homes are boarded up while we watch our
neighbors sleeping on the streets.
The cancellation of state housing builds means that the homelessness crisis is
going to get even worse. We know this because it's exactly what
happened last time government stopped building state housing.
We saw more and more people sleeping on the streets and in their
cars.
Move in orders are not only cruel, they're ineffective.
Our town and city centers are not struggling because there are people who are
sleeping on the streets. People are sleeping on the streets for the
same reason that shops are struggling to keep their doors open.
An economic system where the super wealthy are siphoning more and more from
everyday people and from the state, while we've struggled with the cost of living
crisis.
Rents are high, wages and incomes are low, and people cannot afford
the basics. Instead of addressing the cost of living pressures that
drive our neighbors, our young people, our whanau into homelessness,
it means that many of us cannot afford to spend money in our local businesses and
our town and centers. This government is choosing to push forward with these
move on orders to give a kind of false perception of economic improvement by
hiding away the very visible proof of a very unequal
system.
When safe, secure housing is out of reach, the answer cannot be to
criminalize. People need care, support, and real
pathways into homes. We deserve a housing system that
ensures that everyone has a place to live with dignity and security,
and we deserve leadership that prioritizes people's wellbeing and our shared
future over short-term optics.
Aotearoa has one of the lowest percentage of public and community housing in the
OECD, making up only 3.8% of our housing
stock.
Instead of passing legislation and using our collective resources to criminalize
homelessness, we should be building public housing at scale, not
only to house those who are sleeping on the streets and who are on the wait list,
but to provide decent and stable homes to the many people in our communities
struggling to afford the rent at the moment.
Building public housing at scale not only means decent homes for everyone,
it creates jobs. It will make our town and city centers spaces
where everyone, no matter their income, can afford to live and
contribute to their creativity and vibrancy.
As mentioned in my submission, the government has the resources and scale to build
enough public housing so that everyone has a decent
home. I also join with my colleagues who
have been calling for duty to assist legislation so that all
public and community services have a duty to not only prevent homelessness,
but to provide immediate housing support and keep people on the books to
ensure that people have permanent housing.
I urge the government to uphold Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
The report back from the Waitangi Tribunal housing policy and
services inquiry, W2750, made it clear that decisions that
will lead to an increase in houselessness for whanau Maori
is a breach of Article 2 and 3 of Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
Move on orders will make Maori houselessness worse in this country.
The orders are also a breach of the Bill of Rights, specifically that moving
people on for begging appears inconsistent with the right of freedom of
expression, and that precluding a person from staying or entering a
specified area appears inconsistent with the right
to freedom of movement.
We at Public Housing Futures believe that the solution is to build
public housing to ensure that people have access to
really good quality, decent homes,
as opposed to
creating a legislation that will displace and move
people further away from their networks and the services that allow them to
thrive. We know that building public housing will not only
ensure that people who are currently homeless have access to decent
homes, it will actually make our city and town centers beautiful,
vibrant, thriving spaces for everyone.
So, we oppose the Summary Offences
Amendment Bill and urge the committee to drop it.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you, Vanessa. Thank you also for that
research around the census information that you've shared there.
I personally haven't heard of that duty to assistance
legislation. I don't know if you can tell me where that-- has
that been implemented in other places, somewhere
the committee could be looking about that?
Yes. So, in Wales, duty to assist legislation has
been created, and it's really about ensuring that
our public and community services, if someone walks in
to, say, work and income, and says that
they are going to lose their home if they can't get rent
arrears paid, it ensures that our systems make sure that those rent
arrears are paid so that people can stay in their home,
so that it can prevent homelessness.
But also, if someone's come in and they are without
shelter, that people are put into immediate housing.
But this kind of legislation has to happen alongside a
program to build more public housing so that people are put in
permanent and secure housing.
Thank you, Vanessa. I think I took Dan Rosewarne's question.
I think that was his. I'm getting the thumbs up there.
So, I thank you very much for your time today, and your submission.
We're now going to head to Margie Jean Malcolm for a
five-minute submission. So, we'll just wait for Margie to come online.
Tena koutou katoa.
Welcome, Margie. We're with you for the next five minutes.
Please just go over the summary of your submission, and there may be
some questions from the committee, so we're in your hands.
Okay.
Ko Margie Jean Malcolm ahau. With my tipuna, my
whanau, and my Quaker values of manaakitanga, kaitiakitanga,
and aroha ki nga tangata katoa, I come today to
name this bill as morally indefensible, legally
unnecessary, and fiscally irresponsible.
I speak as someone who's privileged to have a warm home in a community where I have
a sense of security and belonging, and as someone who has worked
voluntarily to support affordable community housing initiatives
since the early 1980s.
I come to urge this committee to firstly, completely withdraw
this bill, and secondly, to listen to the voices of the
homeless and the housing and social service providers who
work to support those struggling, not only on the streets, but with the
many unseen layers of housing insecurity, and work together on
three things.
Firstly, to co-design and put in place a robust Aotearoa
plan to end homelessness.
Secondly, to build a solid bipartisan public community and
kaupapa Maori housing policy, regulatory, and funding
environment.
And thirdly, to develop and implement what you've just been talking about, a
duty to assist legislation as an overarching responsibility
for public institutions to assist people and to secure
accommodation.
And to those who say there is no alternative to pushing ahead with
this bill, I say look what happened in the UK two
weeks ago. England and Wales have just repealed a
200-year-old vagrancy act that criminalized rough sleeping and
begging, acknowledging that homeless people are not criminals,
they are people who need help.
They're shifting from punishment to prevention of homelessness,
focusing on what they know works through providing support for people
to rebuild their lives. Despite a challenging
fiscal environment like we face here, they're investing in a
nationwide plan to end homelessness and expanding social
housing investment that will help people into secure permanent housing.
An Aotearoa plan to end homelessness must be informed by the voices of
those with lived experience of rough sleeping and those delivering
day-to-day prevention and support services.
Joined up kaupapa Maori community, local, and central government
responses must recognize the huge regional variation
in existing service availability and support local
leadership. Ending homelessness must include supporting
people better when they get out of prison, or after hospital stays, or
when exiting any public institution, and address specific
needs of homeless women and children who are often
experienced domestic abuse, of
rangatahi, and of older adults too.
Ending homelessness will also require enhanced respect for the work
of kaupapa Maori community housing and social support
providers who've been swimming upstream in a policy and funding
environment for decades that has never been particularly supportive.
These initiatives should never be seen as a substitute for solid public
housing provision, but rather as an important part of the mix
of locally led solutions.
This bill pushes vulnerable people away from support and into being
criminals. It comes with enormous fiscal and human costs,
requiring government investment in a costly prison pathway, while
making it even harder
for people who are already struggling to rebuild their lives.
And it comes at a time when the current government spending on services to support
people in homelessness has been reduced by almost $80
million compared to two years ago.
Neither are fiscally responsible investments of government
resources.
And as others have already explained, we already have powers in
other laws to tackle disorderly behavior.
In conclusion, I would argue that begging and rough sleeping are a symptom of a
system that has failed to address the traumatic impacts of colonization,
abuse in state care, domestic violence, and many, many more
things. Instead, we have policies that entrench poverty and
inequity. We cannot avoid the uncomfortable reality of
our inequitable society by putting homeless people out of sight and
out of mind.
None of us benefit from a growing prison population, rise in
mental health, violence, homelessness in children living in poverty.
An equal society is better for everyone.
I urge you to withdraw this bill and to invest in robust public
policy and plans to end homelessness, and to provide stable,
affordable housing where all people feel they can belong and
find community support.
Nō reira, nau te rourou, naku te rourou, ka ora
ai te iwi. By working together, we can all flourish.
Well done, Margie. That was very clear, and
right on the five minutes, so thank you very much for your submission today.
Right. Committee, we have our next submitter, Simone
Ackermann. We'll just wait for Simone to come online.
Hello.
Hi, Simone. Welcome to the Justice Committee.
We've got you for the next five minutes.
Please, I'll just let you know if you're getting close to the five minutes.
Otherwise, there may be some questions from the committee.
Yeah. Thank you. Thank you for your time.
This is my first time doing this sort of thing, so please bear with me if I
get anything
wrong, and yeah, feel free to cut in at any time.
So kia ora,
committee members and officials. My name is Simone Ackermann.
I'm a schoolteacher. Before this, I was a professional triathlete
for about 10 years, which culminated me competing at the
Tokyo Olympic Games.
I've spent most of my life in Whangarei.
Generally, I love it there. But today I'm here to advocate
for myself, my parents, who at the time were healthcare
workers, and our close community.
As a teacher, I work daily with a wide
demographic, including youth, who can be highly disruptive.
I have to enforce the rules
and guidelines so students can learn, but I also have to live with my
own conscience,
knowing that some students haven't left home in the right state to learn.
I understand the immense complexities facing our communities, the police,
and local councils.
But I'm here today because for 18 months, I feel that the system dropped
the ball, and our community was left unprotected.
Starting in late 2023, a public reserve in
Orahi was effectively taken over by long-term vehicle
encampments,
where the community was subjected to relentless and
loud music through the night,
forcing us as frontline public servants to work on three hours of sleep.
We were subjected to drinking, drug-taking, and fighting directly
beside a children's playground.
Vandalism, including human feces being smeared over public
toilets.
Intimidation, verbal abuse, and midnight property
trespassing. We also witnessed individuals masturbating out
their vehicles in full view of families at playgrounds.
We did not sit back. We contacted the local council countless
times, thousand times. I went in there.
We met with counselors. We phoned and visited the police.
We distributed pamphlets through the neighborhood. We got signage erected.
We engaged with our local MP, Dr. Reddy.
We even held a community meeting where there was about 30 residents,
the council staff, and the police who all attended.
Yet the obstacle we faced was always the same.
The current law does not allow for immediate meaningful action.
The system simply has no teeth to deal with the sort of
issues we encountered.
Our story is not an isolated one. It is playing out across the country,
affecting families and businesses alike.
This isn't something local councils can fix with piecemeal
bylaws. They lack the enforcement power to deal with the aggressive,
non-compliant behavior that ourselves and other encounters.
We need a national law that empowers police to protect our
neighborhoods.
The bill that we're talking about today does not aim to hide
any complex social issues. It focuses on the harmful behavior and
the individuals who choose to engage in it.
I understand we must work within the Bill of Rights to be fair to the
disadvantaged, while also upholding the King's Peace, which is
the foundational role of the New Zealand Police.
Our neighborhood didn't object to people needing a place to stay.
In fact, our community and the council reached out to social services to
provide help to those people who were in our area,
but that help was repeatedly refused.
They chose to stay and continue their damaging behavior.
As a teacher, I refuse to accept that severe antisocial abuse
should be tolerated as a standard symptom of living in your vehicle.
It is not a license to tyrannize neighborhoods and the families that live within
them. When a playground becomes unsafe,
everyday families lose their public spaces.
Frontline workers like my family, other families in the community, and
Langatahi have a right
to safety, peace, and sleep too.
In a classroom, I understand that clear boundaries are how
we support positive behavior in our students.
And our communities deserve those exact same boundaries.
So therefore, I strongly support the Summary Offences
Amendment Bill.
I support Section 8A to move people on for
disruptive behavior, and Section 8C to stop transient
individuals escaping accountability by refusing their details.
I also strongly support the intent to inhibit a public space.
This provision directly protects public spaces,
ensuring they stay open, clean, and safe for all the community to
enjoy.
There's two sort of amendments that I would recommend.
I think a lot of the bill focuses on the CBDs and the business
areas. Our experience shows that it also affects
residential neighborhoods, and I would like this to also be
explicitly included,
because I think suburban families deserve the exact same peace and safety.
And then also, my understanding is there is a bit of a freedom
camping loophole. I think council camping designation
must never be used as a license to behave disorderly.
All individuals should face the
same laws.
So-
Simone, we've got a
question online. So we're just nearing time, so I'd just like to
take that question if we can. Todd Stevenson, please.
Oh, hi Simone. Thank you for your submission.
Hi.
Obviously, you've given us a real-life example.
So in your case,
you could clearly differentiate...
Obviously, there are people that are homeless, and they've got a genuine
homelessness problem.
Yeah.
But in your case, this was different.
You basically talked about this bill could address
the antisocial and disorderly behavior that you witnessed.
Is that kind of how you... You see those things as quite separate.
Yes.
I guess they're tied in that some of the people
were homeless and behaving in a certain way.
But to answer your question directly, I see it as a way to
address the behavior that was associated.
It wasn't just explicitly people living in their
vehicles that were dealing in that way, but it became a
thing where because there were people living there, other people would
come and engage in that same behavior.
It created a, what's the word I'm looking for?
A permission system for others to come and behave in that
way. And continually, there was no
pushback. There was no permanent, for lack of a better word,
solution. And so
the environment in
our neighborhood just slowly decreased. People were scared to walk.
When they were out walking, they'd be intimidated.
People would change the direction they would walk.
Families avoided going to the neighborhood.
It just sort of slowly declined, and it took
a long time. Things have started to get better now, but it's having to
take us as a community to continually
... council the staff to kind of maintain that.
And
it's still not perfect, but yeah, it's been a long road, and
it leaves you exhausted.
Thank you.
Well, thank you very much, Simone, for your submission today.
Thank you for the amendments. That was very well done for your first attempt, so
we'll welcome you back in the future on future bills.
Committee, we're now going to head to the Housing and Health Research Program,
University of Otago. I've got
Professor Neville Pearce and Kimberly O'Sullivan,
so we'll just wait for them to come online.
Kia ora
Tena koutou.
Welcome. Neville, I can see you and your colleague.
We've got you for 10 minutes. I think you know the drill.
If we get up to about eight, nine minutes gone, I'll just give you a cue,
otherwise there'll be some questions from the committee. Thank you.
Kia ora.
Tena koutou committee. Ko Neville Pearce taku ingoa.
I'm a professor of public health at the University of Otago, Wellington, and
accompanying me is Dr. Kimberly O'Sullivan.
Thank you very much for the opportunity to appear today on behalf of my
entire Housing and Health Research Group, and many of my research
colleagues.
A few weeks ago, when I arrived at work in the morning, there was a
15-year-old girl sleeping outside our building.
She wasn't causing trouble. She wasn't threatening anyone.
She was not blocking the doorway. She was simply a young person with no place
safe to go.
That experience is relevant to this because this bill would
make her behavior a criminal matter for enforcement and punishment rather than
care and support.
It shifts our response from asking why a child is sleeping on the street
outside and what support they need, to
treating their presence in a public place as a problem.
Our research has shown, and others has consistently shown,
that the answer to homelessness is housing and support.
By every measure when permanently housed, people do better.
Hospitalizations are reduced by half, mental health is massively improved,
police offenses are reduced, and employment jumps.
The answer to a rough sleeping 15-year-old girl is care and
support, not a $2,000 fine or three months in prison.
Unfortunately, people
sleeping rough is not a hypothetical issue in New Zealand.
The people affected by this bill are often amongst the most vulnerable members of
our communities. They are people facing poverty, trauma, family
breakdown, mental distress, and a severe shortage of safe and affordable housing.
Criminalizing people for being visibly poor and homeless does not resolve these
needs. It simply moves people on without addressing the reasons they
are there and the support they need.
I would ask the committee to consider whether criminalizing the visible signs of
homelessness will resolve any of the underlying problems.
Our view is that it will not.
Instead, it makes the solution of
getting people into housing harder for those who are supporting them, and for those
people who are already struggling, and further marginalizing
those in most need. Thank you very much, and I hope that's
plenty of time for questions.
Thank you very much. We do have a question from Carl Bates.
Kia ora, Carl.
Thanks, Chair. Neville, appreciate your submission.
Can you just explain for me, though, how this bill
criminalizes homelessness per se?
So if you take the example you shared of the 15-year-old girl,
if you'd helped her out, that's fantastic, and acknowledge your citizenship.
If you'd asked her to move on,
and she did, there'd be no impact. So I'm missing the
direct connection between the bill and homelessness being
criminalized.
Yes, certainly. So, this bill, as it is
written is, to my eyes, the first piece of legislation
where sleeping has come before the Justice Committee.
In the wording it says
that rough sleeping is one of the things that it seeks to prevent.
And the idea of a move on order is that
somebody either obeys the move on order,
or the punishment is a $2,000
fine or three months in prison. To be honest with you, many
of the people who are sleeping rough, and this girl that we were talking
to, have suffered trauma, and immediate
trauma that won't be diagnosed quickly or easily.
They need support and talking to
get them to engage with services.
This bill enables a police response to that, not a support
response to that.
The police officer
enforcing this bill
will ask somebody to move on. If because of
the trauma and because of the place they're in, they're not able to, the
response in this bill is a fine and imprisonment.
I suggest that that 15-year-old girl did not have $2,000.
So what you are looking at there on this bill is an
imprisonment of a 15-year-old girl who is not causing any trouble.
And I think that that's the bit where I find difficulty with your argument,
is that you jump straight from this is happening
to she would end up in prison.
And not
that, A, she would have the choice to move on,
or secondly, that this is giving police a tool
to support people like her. For example, if she was in Whanganui to get to the new
crisis cafe opened under this government.
And then I also wonder if you have any consideration in
that for if that scenario had been outside
a dairy or a business
where that individual is not just sleeping, and
therefore there's a challenge that needs to be supported through some of the
other things that the government has been doing, which this bill's not about,
around housing,
but is disrupting people entering that premise,
is disrupting people wanting to go into that dairy and buy things,
and
therefore should see the individual
creating that disturbance moved on from that premise, and
what consideration you have for those scenarios.
I'll ask my colleague Kim to answer that, please.
The research that we've done with young people, most of
those young people described having one of two options.
The first was to stay somewhere where they were very unsafe,
or to move somewhere else where they didn't necessarily have
a roof for the night, and that put them at extreme
vulnerability to abuse and victimization.
If the solution that you're seeking is to find a
place for that 15-year-old girl to go to, moving her into a
dark corner is not going to help us find that.
And so I think the issue is around the behavior,
but the behavior of sleeping, I would argue is
not going to be offensive. It's not going to be
obstructive.
Our issue is with making rough sleeping a part of this law,
and I think that there are other ways that we can
address the behavior and the antisocial behaviors without
including sleeping as a part of this.
I have two more questions. I'd just like to get to them.
So I'll go to Dan and then Camilla.
Thanks, Chair. Just further along with that, what do you think are the likely
consequences for a young person who is sleeping rough,
then they receive a move on order, then they end up with police contact
or contact with the justice system just because they had nowhere else
safe to go?
So
as a statistician, I can confidently tell you that somebody
who is homeless,
who is experiencing homelessness, if they are moved
on to permanent sustainable housing, will have much the same likelihood
of criminal offenses as the rest of us.
If they are not
in permanent sustainable housing or if they're moved on like this bill goes
and they get their first offense, they will go to be 12 times more
likely to be seen in the justice system repeatedly again.
This first offense makes it harder for them to enter the
private rental market and escape their homelessness in future after
they've seen out their prison term.
That makes them more likely to go into crime again and
harder to get out of. Also, a $2,000 debt that is
unpayable is a barrier to creating a bond or to
escaping homelessness in the private rental market.
These punishments are not supportive.
They're punishments, and they're not helpful to helping support people.
Camilla, can we have your question, please?
Thank you. Thanks for your submission, and answers to questions as well.
I just had a question around your recommendations, but also to
note
some of the
obstruction of an entranceway of a building and
also a public way is currently covered by existing law.
But my question was really,
you've suggested in recommendation three that
removing rough sleeping, begging, and I think it was also in
recommendation two, the 18-year-olds from the ...
Sorry, 14 to 18-year-olds from this legislation
would kind of remove most of your concerns with this bill.
I
appreciate the overall thing is that it's withdrawn, but would that kind of address
most of the concerns that you,
well, the major concerns you have with the bill?
That would,
in my opinion, reduce all the new elements of the bill,
and I acknowledge that everything else is basically
covered under existing legislation.
So yes.
I'd prefer the bill was removed because I don't think it's a helpful statement to
make,
but that would remove the
elements of this bill that are most likely to add harm to people.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Nevil and Kimberly, for your submission.
Really good questions as well, so thank you.
The committee's going to move on to Vicki Tyrrell, so we'll just wait for Vicki
to come online. Thank you.
Kia ora.
Welcome. I'm not seeing you, Vicki.
Maybe you've got your camera off. I can't see you.
I-
There you are. I can see you. Welcome.
I can see you.
Welcome. We've got you for five minutes today.
We're willing to hear what you've got to say, and we may have some
questions for you. So away we go. Thank you.
Kia ora. Thank you for the
opportunity to speaking
to you today. I
am
veteran Vicki Tyrrell. As
you can hear, I have a
speech impairment, so
I had
prepared a pre-written
paper to help with the
communicating.
I take my written
submission as being
read.
I want to
add to the reality of
rough
sleeping,
and I acknowledge
In preparing it,
I looked at a
recent interview between
Helen Wappinton of the
Auckland City Mission
and Tony
Manhire.
Not having housing
is
only a symptom of
rough
sleeping.
People
who are homeless
become homeless because they
are in poverty and have
trauma. Some of the
trauma might be poor
mental health, physical
health issues, addiction
issues, relationship
breakdown.
Lots
of the job and no
resources.
They
don't have
a safe place to live.
If we
were homeless
or needed a place
to
stay for tonight or two,
we
probably could stay with
family or
friends,
and we would have support
to get back into
secure housing
pretty quickly. But
people who are rough
sleeping don't.
Primarily,
it's a health
issue. People do not have
choices as to where to
sleep tonight.
People
sometimes
being released from
hospital or jail
do not have anywhere
to go.
So,
suddenly loss of
income
because of
losing a job,
and if you're a renter,
means
you lose your home
pretty quickly. Some
people have been on the
street for years,
and
for a number of reasons
may reject help.
Living on the street might
be preferable to living in
hostile, supporting
houses where there is
violence.
Some people
who have learned to live
on the street, keeping
themselves
safe because there is no
other
safe option.
And
moves on orders will
not
solve the rough sleeping
issue. It may make
it more difficult for people
to get the help they need
because
they need to keep moving.
And what
a safe
realistically
safe
spot they were
sleeping in, they made a
home in.
So, in not causing
trouble may,
indeed.
Thank you very-
They may need to be moved on
to
an unsafe
situation.
That is my
oral submission.
Thank you very much, Vicky, and for your summary
of the bill and your thoughts. That will be taken into
consideration by the committee. Thank you very much for your time today.
Thank you.
Okay.
Our next submitter, committee, is Te Rangi
Cleaver, so we'll just wait for them to come online.
Kia ora.
Welcome. Thank you very much. We've got five minutes of your time
today. There may be some questions from the committee.
I'll let you know if any hands go up, but we're in your hands
now.
Kia ora. Ko Te Rangi ahau. He uri ahau nō Ngāti Kahungunu ki
Wairoa. I am a poet, so my kupu comes from my puku.
So here we go.
You can't beat a good day in Wellington, and they're right.
A good day in Wellington is generous.
The city stretches itself out like a cat in a warm window.
Cuba Street hums. Students are asleep in patches of sun.
Children shriek through the bucket fountain. People simply exist together.
And apparently, that's what these move on orders are here to protect.
Everyday people is the phrase that I've heard.
Everyday people. Everyday people. Everyday people.
I keep turning it over on my tongue until it cuts the roof of my mouth,
trying to work out who falls through the gap between every and day, because
every day I see people carrying everything they own inside a
backpack. Every day I see people being failed by this government.
Every day someone survives another day.
If you sleep rough every day, surely you're an everyday person.
If addiction follows you home, then reminds you, you don't have one, surely you're
an everyday person. Every day these people exist.
It's just not every day that this government admits they do.
Maybe this bill isn't about protecting people.
Maybe it's about protecting plausible deniability, protecting the illusion
that if suffering keeps moving, it will eventually disappear.
You can't beat a good day in Wellington, and maybe that's true, but this government
seems intent on finding out who can be beaten to protect one.
Move on. Like this country wasn't built by telling one people to move
on so another could move in. As though colonialism wasn't the longest
running move on order this land has ever known. Move on.
And now I can't stop thinking about how strange that instruction sounds when you're
already standing at the end of the road beyond the map, where every direction is
another form of falling. It's hard to pull someone back when both their
hands are already losing their grip.
Hard to compete with bright pokies machines designed to
recognize desperation, that swallow money and hope.
Hard to compete with despair, with loneliness.
Hard to compete with a system that manufactures cliffs, then blames people for
falling off the edge. And still, you tell us it's cheaper to move
someone on than to move them into a home. Except it isn't.
A house has always been cheaper, but nothing is cheaper than this house's
excuses. Move on where?
The question no one seems interested in answering. Move on where?
Move on to another doorway. Move on to another warning, another fine they
cannot pay. Move on to another park bench until someone else decides that bench
belongs to everyday people. Move on out of sight, out of mind, out of
options. Move on so the rest of us can move on.
Move on to another waiting list. Move on to the emergency room.
Move on to the back of a police car. Move on to the courtroom.
Move on to the prison. Keep moving.
Keep complying with an instruction that has no destination
until exhaustion finishes the job that policy started, until there's
nowhere left to move except to the coffin.
Just somewhere where the rest of us do not have to watch you die, and then tell
me that this is about public safety.
Tell me this is about protecting everyday people.
Each time I hear it, the definition seems to shrink because there are
no everyday people. There are only people.
People who were once children before this country turned them into a
statistic. And when politicians fail the people, they have a habit of
describing them as criminals, and nothing terrifies a failing policy
more than the people forced to survive it.
So I'll keep asking you all the question this bill keeps stepping
around. Move on?
Move on where? And I will not be taking any questions. Thank you.
Thank you very much for your submission.
Thank you.
We are now heading onto
Pillar New Zealand,
and we'll just wait for them to come online.
I think it's Nathan and Aryan.
Good morning. Can you hear me?
Oh, welcome, Aryan. Welcome to the Justice Committee.
We've got you for 10 minutes today.
Do we have a colleague as well coming online?
It'll just be me this morning.
Okay. Welcome indeed. Please leave us some time.
I'll probably let you know with about eight minutes gone, and if there's
any questions pop up, I'll let you know as well. Thank you.
Well, thank you for the opportunity to speak to this legislation.
I won't be as probably poetic and beautifully presented as the last one,
but I hope it's still of value.
My name is Aryan, I'm here on behalf of Pillar New Zealand.
Pillar stands for Protecting Individual Life, Liberty and Rights.
We're a civil liberties outfit that believes that New Zealand has inherited a
wonderful heritage of democracy and liberty, and so we hope to preserve
that. From the outset, I'd like to
affirm that we're understanding of the motivations behind this bill and the goal
that is being pursued. Disorderly behavior in public that is left
unchallenged
reduces the public's enjoyment of public spaces and interferes with
commercial activity of local businesses and can instill a
sense of fear and danger in our urban areas, which affects, again, not just
businesses, but also families and individuals who are looking to
use and enjoy these spaces. Of course, safer central business
districts is a desirable goal to pursue.
However, the current wording of this legislation, we believe,
sets a poor legal precedent when it comes to the protection of civil liberties here
in New Zealand. Therefore, as sympathetic as we are to the goals being pursued,
we do not support the bill in its current form.
There are three first principles which guide our concerns and Also will
guide our recommendations, as you would've seen in the written
submission. Those are freedom of expression, freedom of movement, and right to
assembly, and legal proportionality and natural justice.
And that last point on legal proportionality is an issue that you'll see as
a running thread throughout our concerns.
Firstly, with regard to free speech, we're heartened by the protection
for protests. So we appreciate that, and I'm aware that that's in
the legislation. However, we are concerned by the proposed definition of
begging. As drafted, the bill extends beyond regulating
harmful conduct, and instead captures forms of peaceful expression,
including simply holding a sign or expressing personal need.
New Zealanders, including those who are socially or economically
deprived,
who would, for example, be beggars, have the right to express their need,
whether with speech or with writing on a sign.
Under the current provisions of this bill, begging alone, even passively with no
disruption,
could be legally punishable.
Now, with the current wording, we see ultimately the government arbitrating what
speech is acceptable within society and what speech is not acceptable.
That's the message I believe that is being sent.
And that's measured against its own political objectives.
As a matter of principle, this is a dangerous line of thinking to allow into the
legislative drafting
process that suggests where
speech and expression is an inconvenient obstacle to the
desired goals of the government, it can or even should be
suppressed.
So we believe that there's a very important and clear distinction between
conduct that is actually intimidating or interferes with others, and
speech that some may just find uncomfortable.
If we are to penalize anything, it ought to be activity,
not expression. And some might say, "Oh, look,
you're making a big deal out of this."
We believe that this is not the case.
The gang patch legislation that was passed earlier in this term, as an
example of even the attorney general agreeing that it was a suppression
on speech rights. And there are political arguments for and
against it, but we just see how this type of thinking can seep into the legislative
process.
And so again, we believe this is a slippery slope, and the
attorney general certainly, in his comments, has come to a similar conclusion
and believes that we can take a less rights intrusive approach
with regard to that. When it comes to freedom of movement and the
right to assembly, the legislation provides insufficient guidance to police
officers as to the geographical scope of a move on order.
That's not specified in the bill in its current writing at the moment, creating
uncertainty as to how far an individual may be required to leave a
particular location. For those experiencing homelessness or rough sleeping or
begging, being removed from an area may also mean being separated from
essential services or support that may be available nearby.
This doesn't mean that police should not have the power to intervene, obviously,
but rather where and when they do, their powers must be clearly defined,
proportionate, and at least considerate of the practical consequences of
displacement, including the individual's ability to access services.
Again, the current wording just doesn't achieve this
and doesn't do this. So again, as I said earlier, a less rights
infringing approach is possible, can be pursued, but
has not been done here,
and threaten civil liberties.
And finally, as I said, a running theme is that of legal proportionality and
natural justice.
This is most evidently clear in the penalties imposed by this
legislation for those in breach of move on orders.
Currently, the penalties for breaching an order sit alongside for penalties
for offenses that are significantly more serious, including
careless driving causing death or dealing class C drugs.
The regulatory impact statement shows that
of the options given to him, the minister has chosen the most aggressive
legislative path. We suggest that there are alternatives that can be
pursued and should be considered.
The sanctions proposed, in our view, are not proportionate to the conduct
being punished and exemplifies, again, a lack of constraint in
wielding the coercive power of the state.
Again,
you hear me saying this a lot, but there are less rights
infringing alternatives that can be pursued and should be pursued.
And so with that, look, my recommendations or our recommendations are
there. Much of it is around redrafting and using more clear terms,
and providing more guidance and just taking an approach that is more
proportionate when it comes to exercising or wielding the coercive power
of the state.
We ultimately believe that countries that value both liberty and democracy
have to be vigilant when it comes to wielding the coercive power of the state.
This bill, in its current form, fails that test of vigilance.
And so with that, I'm happy to take any questions.
We've got a couple questions for you, Aaron.
We'll start with Camilla, and then we'll go to Dan.
Thank you so much for your submission.
Apologies if I missed it, because I think we did a quick tiny power cut
here at Parliament.
Yeah.
But, I was really interested in the points that you made
around protests and how this potentially might affect
counter-protests. And so I just wondered if you could expand on that
slightly to make sure we can get some advice on your exact concern.
Yeah. Look, there is obviously that section that
provides protection for expressing ideas.
Where that gets a little bit murky is around what if there is someone who is
begging but also protesting
homelessness. That can be a bit murky.
But also there are certain terms here that are left undefined when it comes to
disorderly behavior or breaching the peace
If it is left undefined as it currently is in this
legislation, what happens is we have ultimately an arbitrary
application of the law and an imposition of a police officer in
Palmerston North might decide, "Actually, this is what breaching the peace is," and
a police officer in Auckland might decide that
this is what it is. And in both cases, we've seen in the past, there are
legal cases which are quite high profile, I won't name them here, I don't need to,
but
where someone holding a sign has been punished by police for
breaching peace, and those are actually going through the courts at the moment.
And so, again, it just comes to actually being vigilant when it comes to writing
legislation and being more considerate of these realities.
And so that's, yeah.
Dane Rosewarne, please.
Thanks for touching on the potential for a move on order,
like attracting penalties that are comparable to some much
more serious offenses. You're the first person that's actually raised that with the
committee
this morning, and I'll be keen to get some more advice from officials
on that. I'm just wondering if you could provide some more context
around why you consider those penalties disproportionate, and what
impact you think that that could actually have in practice.
Well, look,
one of the tests of good legislation is it's proportionate.
And that's not to say that
police shouldn't have the ability to exercise the punitive power of the
state. But at the moment, someone going to jail for
three months, which is one of the proposals under this
legislation, could happen for just holding up a sign
that's requesting money or begging as is the case
under section 8A (1)
. So look, the reality is that's just far too punitive, far too fast
for something that is far too little.
That's not to say that we can't ... The regulatory impact statement shows that
there are three other options that could be pursued with far less
imposition
from the state. And so I just think it's far too much for far too little.
Thank you. That's very helpful.
We've got one last question. We've only got about 45 seconds left, but Carl Bates,
please.
Thanks, Chair. I've got three quick parts to my question.
Why do you think submitters who've been submitting against us throughout the
morning have continually referenced the idea, like you just
have, that there would be three months
in prison for holding up a sign when that's not actually what the offense would be
for? Why do you think they ignore the role this gives police to
help people find the assistance they need, like the
crisis cafes? And C, why do you think submitters are not taking
into account or not commenting on the impact on families who
have small businesses that are currently being affected
by people begging at the doors of their
stores?
Look, I appreciate the question. I'm in no position to answer on behalf of
anyone else. Look,
the reality is these are our concerns, and we are appreciative of the fact that
businesses are impacted by this as well.
And so we do have to balance the rights of the different parties
here. The way we do that is through vigilance and through
good legal writing, and this bill does not do that.
I'm sorry, I won't be able to comment on-
No worries
... what others have said, but this is just the way it is at the moment. Thank you.
Okay.
Thank you very much, Aaron, and for Pillar's submission.
You've been submitting to a number of bills, and they've been very well,
the way you're setting them out, so well done on that.
So thank you for your time today.
Awesome. Thank you so much, guys.
Right. Our next submitter members is the
Christchurch Methodist Mission.
We're waiting on Jill and Jane, so we'll just wait for them to
join.
They are on screen.
They're on screen. Jill, Jane.
We're here.
Welcome. I can't see you. Maybe it's a camera. If you could turn your camera on.
I can see Dr Laurence, who's just joined us. Welcome.
Otherwise, if you don't want to have the camera on, we can just do it the
just by sound.
We can see you, Mr Chair.
We can see them. Their camera is on.
You can see them? For some reason I can't.
But anyway, welcome to the Justice Committee.
We've got 10 minutes with you today, and we'll lead you into
the submissions, and there'll probably be some questions at the end as
well.
Kia ora koutou, and thank you for hearing our submission this morning.
I'm called Jill Hoki Tokonga. I'm the director of the Christchurch Methodist
Mission.
I'm called Jane Higgins, Toko Ingoa.
I'm the strategic advisor for the Christchurch Methodist Mission.
Welcome.
The Methodist Mission has been the lead agency for Housing First in
Christchurch and in Blenheim for the last eight years.
During that time, we've housed close to 600 people who were long-term
homeless, and today we're providing ongoing support to
430 people.
Last year, additional government funding enabled us to establish an
outreach team in Christchurch, where over the last nine months
we've been able to support a further 80 people, half whom we've
found housing for.
Overall, we're managing to find housing for approximately
20 to 25 people per month. That's at least one
person every working day that we're moving into housing.
But our challenge is that double that number are coming through our door.
Currently, we've got 250 people on our waiting
list for housing in Christchurch.
That's 250 people sleeping on the streets,
under bushes in the park, under disused railway bridges.
Some have a car that they can sleep in, while others may have
friends whom they can stay with for a few nights before going back to the
streets
One third are women.
At least 50% are Maori, and we're seeing an
increasing number of older people.
It's these 250 people who we are particularly
concerned about when considering this bill.
This legislation will place these people in danger by forcing them to move
from relatively safe, well-lit, and populated areas of our cities
to much less safe areas, such as parks, bridges, and so
forth. The regulatory impact statement accompanying the bill says
groups that are particularly at risk include women, young people, those who are
disabled, those experiencing mental ill health.
We concur,
and as Jill has said, we would like to add to this list a growing and alarming
number of older people that we are seeing who are sleeping rough.
Housing First Ōtautahi has seen the results of violence experienced
by homeless women.
We have seen through our youth hub many vulnerable young people
who do not choose to live on the streets.
By the time they arrive there, they've exhausted all options for safe
shelter. They are dangerously exposed to physical violence
and mental trauma. One of the aims of the bill
excuse me,
is to increase the public sense of safety, but it risks sacrificing the
actual safety of a portion of the public who are already highly
vulnerable in order to address often
ill-founded perceptions about safety among a portion of the public who have many
protections available to them to maintain their own safety, not least
a home to return to.
Additionally, we agree with those who have said the bill will effectively
criminalize survival activities undertaken by homeless people in public.
It fails to acknowledge or address the fact that people do this because they have
no safe sheltered alternative.
This kind of enforcement has been tried overseas for similar rationales,
such as the economic health of inner cities, and it has met with poor
results. The evidence simply does not support this approach.
So as Jane has said, this bill will do nothing to address homelessness
and the trauma associated with it, and will instead create
further harm.
Local and international evidence has identified what can be
done to reduce the number of people sleeping on our streets:
safe shelter, permanent housing, early intervention,
and tailored support that
meets the needs of Maori women and other marginalized groups.
Our recommendations are simple.
First, that the bill be withdrawn.
Second, if it does proceed, that young people are
exempt from any move on orders and are instead
referred to a youth service.
That rough sleeping be removed from the definition of
disorderly or disruptive behaviors.
That those who are homeless and come to the attention of the police be connected
with housing and support services before enforcement options
are considered.
And finally, that the government invests further in the provision of
permanent social housing, as well as evidence-based responses
such as Housing First, for those who find themselves homeless.
Our experience over the past eight years has highlighted that
transformation is possible when people are
well-housed and receive appropriate supports.
This bill undermines this work and places
already vulnerable people at further risk.
Thank you, Jill and Jane,
for that. We have a question from Dr Lawrence Yun.
Cool. Kia ora. Thanks, Chair. Thanks, Jill and Jane, and thank you for the
work that you do.
You picked up on kind of right at the end.
Can I just check,
right now there is a huge waiting list, particularly for
seniors on the social housing register.
With this bill, and if, let's say, seniors or young people get moved
on, and if there's already a waiting list, where are they being moved to?
Well, the danger is that they've been moved further away from where we're
actually able to provide support to them.
Often we know that Mrs Smith or Mrs Jones may actually be
sleeping underneath this bush by the railway line, and we'll be able to go and
find her, offer support, offer her housing, and so on.
But if in the meantime during the night the police have come and they've moved her
on to somewhere else, we may not be able to find her the next day.
So our concern is that people actually have safe spaces
where they are actually able to live.
Sorry, Chair. Can I have a follow-up question?
So
what I'm hearing is that there's also mechanisms with your organizations
and potentially others as well that actually tracks, because where they
are sleeping is reasonably a stable, I guess,
location. Consistent is a better word. Consistent location.
And there's a concern that if they get moved on to somewhere else,
that's it. It's going to be randomized.
They're not always consistent, but often there'll be a place that we know that this
particular group of people sleep in this particular place, so we can find them.
Thank you.
You mentioned you service Christchurch and Blenheim,
Blenheim being my hometown. What can you tell us about the
difference maybe between the city and the regional areas
for need?
Very similar.
Blenheim's got a housing shortage.
It's got a shortage of one bedroom homes.
So we find a lot of people either in emergency housing, in transitional housing
that we
have there, or we support them through our Housing First service and try and
find long-term permanent accommodation.
But certainly people on the streets there, and often
again, will go to places where they think they'll be
safe.
Thank you very much. We don't have any further questions for you today,
but thank you very much for your submission.
Thank you.
Thank you. Members, our next
submitter is Sharon Elbourne. So we'll just wait for her to come
online.
Welcome to the Justice Committee.
Just got
your screen. Maybe if you can turn your
camera on.
Yeah.
Can you hear me?
Yes, we can. We've got you for five minutes.
You're most welcome to do the submission like this, or you can flip
the camera on. But you're welcome to start.
Oh, here we are. Go.
Wait one moment. Right.
There you go. We see you now.
Good. Okay.
Right.
Maybe once you get to about four minutes, I'll just give you a prompt.
There may be a question from the committee, but we're in your hands.
Kia ora.
Tēnā koutou katoa. I'm against this bill.
But first, I'd like to sincerely thank the committee staff
for organizing the best time for me to be here.
They were so kind to accommodate my needs, and in fact, I
base this oral submission on their kindness.
You see, in our lives, we all have a choice.
We can choose to make someone's life happier through
showing loving kindness and compassion, which the staff did to me,
or we can choose to increase people's suffering through anger,
hatred, and division. And you, as politicians, are
so lucky in that you've got the authority that
not only bring about one person's happiness, but you can
bring about happiness for whole communities through
choosing policies that support rather than diminish.
Now, His Holiness the Dalai Lama says love and
compassion are necessities. They're
not luxuries, because without them, humanity just
cannot survive.
So with this bill, you have the choice of going ahead with it
and increasing the suffering of street dwellers, the coldness,
the hunger, the lack of safety. It must be unbelievably
awful for them. Or you can show kindness and compassion
by ditching this bill and finding kind and
caring solutions.
Now, you'll have roadblocks along the way if you choose
kindness. Your finance minister and the leader of the
Act Party, along with the Minister of Justice, will not
be very happy with the loving kindness and compassion route.
They don't think very highly of people who are vulnerable, people who,
through no fault of their own, struggle in this world.
However, they do exhibit loving kindness and compassion
to some groups. So that ability to reach out is
there, which is heartening.
Your role is to help them reach out to the
vulnerable.
May I make a couple of suggestions as how you could do this?
You could use a quote from Pope Leo, who believes that, in our
time, we still see too much discord, too many wounds
caused by hatred, violence, prejudice, the
fear of the other, and an economic system that
exploits the Earth's resources and
marginalizes the poor.
And on a practical level, you can also point out that
the RIS says that the cost of this bill
outweighs the benefits, and that's not good when trying to
balance the books.
But those costs refer to the immediate costs.
The longer-term costs are huge. Alienation,
poor health, inability to find work or to function
constructively within a community,
and these factors are the key factors when looking at the
causes of crime, addiction, and mental health,
which are more costs.
This bill, I assume, is to keep business owners happy.
They do not like coming to work and having
to step over someone sleeping in the doorway.
They also believe that the presence of
street dwellers causes people not to come to their businesses,
so they lose profit. Now, far be it from me
to judge whether that's the truth or not.
They are feeling this, and that must be taken into
account.
This bill, however, it's not the answer.
It does not need to
pass to get rid of street dwellers.
It will not achieve the same. All it will achieve
is more suffering.
What will achieve the aim of moving street dwellers on
is for you to change your policy settings and find them
warm, dry, and safe accommodation.
It is my view that the leaders of our country, as the leaders of
our country, you have a responsibility to care for us
all, business owners and street dwellers
alike. That's your job.
So your choice is whether to be like your committee staff
and show loving kindness and compassion, or to
implement this bill, which will cause so much
suffering, anxiety, hatred, and
division.
The choice is yours
Please choose your committee as your role model.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Sharon. We've just got time for one quick question from Carl
Bates.
Thanks very much, Chair, and appreciate that this is part of a package of
activity that's happening to support
those that are homeless. I wanted to just ask whether you considered the
2,250 additional social housing
homes committed to in this year's budget by the
Honorable Nicola Willis and the Prime Minister as a demonstration
of their love and kindness for those in need of those
homes.
I think it's fabulous if you're going to build all those houses, but you
need to do them now, and this bill does not
exhibit love and kindness and compassion.
There are many other policies that your government have
implemented that do not indicate love and kindness and
compassion.
So you'd like those homes to be built unlike the
Kiwi home or Kiwi build homes that weren't built.
So point taken.
No, that's not the point I'm making at all.
And that's bringing politics into it.
Well, you're making the point you want to build them
Okay. We'll cut that there. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much, Sharon, for your thoughtful submission.
Members, we're now moving on to the New Zealand Council for
Civil Liberties, Thomas
Beagle. We'll just wait for Thomas to come on board. Yep.
Are you ready there?
Yes. Welcome, Thomas. We've got you for 10 minutes.
If we get near the end of the submission, I'll just give you a prompt if there's
any questions from the committee, but welcome.
Cool. Thank you.
Yes, good morning. I'm Thomas Beagle, and as I said, I'm the chair of the NZ
Council for Civil Liberties. Now, when this bill first came to our attention, we
reviewed the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act, looking for the
right to exist in a public place, and to be honest, we couldn't find it.
But in my opinion, this wasn't because the authors didn't think it should be
included. It was because it was so self-evident it didn't need to be included.
Of course, we have a right to be in public places.
Indeed, you can see this implicit understanding in a number of other rights.
Freedom of movement is meaningless without the right to be in a public space.
Freedom of peaceful assembly, freedom of expression, these all rely-- And of
course, then we get liberty of the person, means that everyone has the right not to
be arbitrarily arrested or detained.
And I argue that also includes the right not to be ejected from a public place or
moved on, in the language of the bill.
Now, we all know that Section 5 of the Bill of Rights says that we can limit
these rights, says it can be justified in a free and democratic society. Of course.
However, we already have a system of laws that establishes limits where people can
be arrested for harassment, threats, disorderly behavior, and the like.
The rest of people go to court, they get tried, and we, of course, we hope justice
is done. There is a process, and there are protections to ensure that the
process is carried out fairly.
This bill turns the police into the entire process from protection
through to punishment. There is no oversight.
There's not even any tracking of the use of these powers.
And by definition, these actions are being taken against the weakest
and most powerless members of our society who do not have the ability or the
social capital to defend themselves.
And none of this applies to begging or sleeping rough.
This appears to be more about protecting society or
stopping aggression or disorderly behavior and punishing people for being poor and
homeless, for being messy and underprivileged in the public eye.
We note that particularly when it comes to begging and rough sleeping, released
documents show that the NZ Police have not sought these powers and seemingly do not
want them. We also note again that when it comes to begging and rough sleeping in
particular, that the Attorney General's Bill of Rights Section 7
report also conclude this bill overly intrudes on our
liberties.
This part of the bill looks vindictive, and it is an embarrassment to our country.
Now, our written submission listed a large number of other ways the bill
potentially infringes on our liberties.
The move on orders, with their blocking of access to places and time limits of when
people cannot return,
can also interfere with people of other rights to exercise their religion, access
medical care, get to their job, talk to a member of parliament, report to their
parole officer, or even enter their own house.
Now, some of these are actually, they might be forced to turn up to their parole
officer or forced to turn up for jury duty, but the move on order might be
banning them from accessing those places. So this is obviously unreasonable.
If you persist in passing this bill, we recommend you add a significant number of
exceptions that will allow people to exercise these rights and
responsibilities without fear of unjustified prosecution.
Now, obviously, at the council, we've got a strong interest in core democratic
rights, including the right to
protest. And we were really pleased to note the bill does include a
clause that prevents move on orders being issued against people engaging in
political protest. However, to complete the protection, it
should also say that those excluded from the area cannot be excluded if
they are there to engage in political protest.
Otherwise, it tends to the situation where people may be a
multi-day protest where people may be cleared out one day and not be able to return
the next.
In conclusion, we oppose this bill as unnecessary.
Police already have the powers to arrest people who are aggressive, commit
violence, or are disorderly.
We do not believe there is a need for additional arbitrary powers to be
exercised against the weak and powerless people without oversight.
They are a recipe for prejudice and abuse.
And it seems to us the bill should be abandoned.
And if not, there needs some serious modifications along the lines suggested by us
and others. At the minimum, begging and rough sleeping should be removed from
the front of the bill.
Thank you for your time. Ask me questions for me.
Thank you very much, Thomas. We do have a few minutes to spare, and we have got a
question from Rima Narkle and then Camilla Belich.
Kia ora, Thomas. So what would you say to the
business owner in South Auckland that has a mortgage, and
has a young child, and has spoken to me,
their local member of Parliament, about the rough
sleepers around their business and how people have said, "Look, we love your
restaurant, but I'm sorry, we feel too uncomfortable to come and
give you business while you have rough sleepers just outside your door." What do
you say to that business owner, Thomas?
I would say that it's a pity that society has failed them by not providing
places for people to sleep.
Failed who?
And it's very sad that people are sleeping rough.
Failed who? Society has failed who?
The people who are sleeping rough and the people who are being affected by that in
a negative way.
But how do you-
I wouldn't think the answer-- I wouldn't say the answer to them and say, "Well, you
should call the police and get moved on to nowhere, because there isn't a place for
them to go."
So we just leave the people there so the person's business can suffer.
Is that what you're saying, Thomas?
Well, just leave-
I'm saying that that frame from, from the policies which lead to rough sleepers
there being there
... let, let them be there. Okay, thank you.
We'll move on to Camilla and then Dr Laurence.
Clever.
Thank you, and thanks for your submission.
I was interested in the point that you made around the preemptive
nature of move on orders, so essentially that they can be
implemented prior to the commission or alleged
commission of a crime. Is that something that you could expand on a little bit?
It's not that. It's more that we're talking about people being excluded from public
places, and possibly the suggestion is that
if people are excluded one day for some arbitrary reason, then that means
they can't obviously arrive there the next day.
Well, that's the point of it, after 24 hours.
If they've got important things they need to be doing there, like I said, visiting
profs or maybe engaged in political protest or anything of that sort, they will
be breaking the law to do so. And we're concerned that, it's like with anything,
there's no oversight on the use of these powers.
We're concerned they could be abused.
Thank you.
Dr Laurence Yunupingu.
Yeah. Thank you so much for your submission, Thomas.
I think my question follows on from what Camilla has asked, which
is,
in your submissions, you talk about the potential fish hooks in this
bill that people may have considered.
I guess, what sort of guideline do you expect should the
bill be implemented? What sort of guidelines do you expect the police to have and
how they're going to be able to judge the nuance?
Well, I think it's a bit unfair pushing it on the police actually.
Mm-hmm.
But that said, there should be more protections for people who
actually have to go to places for reasons.
And like I said, there's an option of being if you were to be, say,
you were to be begging outside your home
and you're given
a move on order, you couldn't return to your home for 24 hours.
Doesn't that seem a bit ridiculous?
We're suddenly turning a beggar into a homeless person.
Or other possible reasons may be maybe they're doing
other areas they might be begging outside their prof.
We shouldn't have the government ordering people to be places where they're also
ordering them not to be. So I think there should be some protections there as well.
There's got to be a good faith defense about why they're
there.
Thank you so much.
Thank you very much, Thomas. We've had a number of questions well
answered, and thank you very much for your submission today.
Thank you. Good luck.
Thank you. Next up, members, is Stephanie Coutts.
We'll just wait for Stephanie to come online.
Tena koutou-
Welcome, Steph
... committee and Chair.
You've got five minutes with us today.
Please leave maybe some time for some questions at the end, but I'll give you a
prompt with about a minute to go.
Thank you, Chair.
My name is Stephanie Coutts. I am speaking here today as an
individual but I do have some experience
working on alternative resolutions in the justice
sector. I've worked at Oranga Tamariki and
on the response to the Royal Commission into abuse in
state care. I'm also on the board of Kaibosh
Food Rescue, and will be supporting their submission after this,
and on the board of the Newtown Community Center.
These are two organizations that work with others,
supporting those in our communities and supporting
those in need.
I have some knowledge, therefore, of homelessness, but I am not
an expert. I urge the committee to listen to the
experts working within our communities to
understand the potential impacts of this bill.
I also urge the committee to seek evidence that the
bill will work, seek evidence from the minister.
His own officials advise that the harms this
bill is likely to cause will outweigh
any benefits. I urge the committee to read
the bill's regulatory impact statement.
I'd like to highlight in the short time I have the potential harm to
young people leaving care. These are the
children of the state. The government is their
parent. These young people are your
children. Very few parents kick their children out
onto the streets when they turn 18, but the state
frequently provides them with few alternatives.
Oranga Tamariki's own assessment of housing supports
available to these young people is dire.
There is no better word for it. The assessment is a couple of
years old, but there is no doubt it has not gotten any
better. Approximately 2,000 young people transition
out of care each year. There are approximately
5,000 young people of the ages to 15 to
20 who are eligible for transition support
The report noted just
134 supported housing places
for these young people. That's approximately
4,800 young people who are the
children of the state pushed into a housing market
that does not cater for them. They are pushed
out of care and often onto the streets.
They are disproportionately Maori
children. The Oranga Tamariki report notes that this
leads to higher rates of homelessness for these young
children.
I have two questions that I'd invite the committee to consider.
When these young people are moved on,
where should they go?
What alternatives do they have?
When they are fined, how will these young
people pay?
The government has said that this bill will not criminalize homelessness,
but it is hard to see it any other way.
The Royal Commission into abuse in state care found that
care was a prison to pipeline.
I invite the committee to consider the commission's report in
the context of this bill. Rather than learn
from the commission, it seems that the government wants to
deny its finding.
I recommend that the committee report back to the House that this
bill should not proceed or should not proceed without
significant amendment. I urge the committee to think
about the children and young people living in precarious
situations, living on our streets, and the impact on them.
Thank you, Chair.
Well done, Steph. I think you've practiced that because you're right on your five
minutes. So thank you very much. The committee doesn't have any questions for you,
but well thought out submission, and thank you for raising those two
questions that I have written down on my sheet. So thank you very much.
Next up, members, is the Kaibosh Food
Rescue. And we're looking for Suzy Robinson.
Tena koutou, can you all hear me?
Welcome. Welcome, Suzy. We've got you for 10 minutes.
We'll just run through your submission as you like.
If we do have some questions, I will let you know with a couple of minutes
to go. So thank you.
Fantastic. Tena koutou, chairperson, ministers, and members
of the committee. Thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
My name is Suzy Robinson, and I'm here to represent Kaibosh Food
Rescue as its chief executive kaiarahi.
I have two board members online with me today, Stephanie Cooks, who
you just heard from, and Ganesh Sanana.
Hopefully, he's here.
Kaibosh are here to strongly urge this committee to recommend
against the proposed move on order legislation, or
at minimum, to significantly amend it.
I'll explain why in the time I have and welcome your questions afterwards.
Kaibosh are not experts in this area, but we work with many who
are, and we also urge you to listen to them as the
experts in the area.
However, we still felt it important to add our voice to this important
matter.
When we see people sleeping in our streets and public spaces,
we are looking at the same reality, a profound national
crisis of housing and public health.
We want communities across Aotearoa that are safe and
thriving. Legislating move on orders does not
solve homelessness, it simply relocates it.
I want to put it simply, practical question to the committee.
When someone is ordered to move on, where exactly are they supposed
to go?
Without a simultaneous sufficient increase in low barrier
beds and permanent supportive housing, a move on order
is, in practice, an order to disappear.
And because people cannot simply disappear, this
legislation will push our most vulnerable neighbors out
of well-lit, relatively safe areas into
unsafe areas, industrial zones, and the margins of our communities,
where without access to community and the support that comes with that,
the risk of harm will be higher.
This legislation will sever support networks that our communities have spent
years building. Take the ecosystem of care
right here in Poneke, Wellington.
Kaibosh Food Rescue works to provide kai to frontline organizations
supporting our whanau without housing.
DCM, who you are hearing from later today, Compassion Soup
Kitchen, Wellington City Mission, The Free Store, Wellington Women's
Homeless Trust, Te Toi Mahanah, Kainga Ora
Housing even, ECTA, and other local food banks,
among many others.
When people are forced to move on, they're disconnected from these
lifelines. A caseworker or volunteer who has spent
weeks building trust could lose contact overnight.
This bill would not clean up our streets.
It would cut people off from kai, medication, and
the very health and social support agencies helping them find a
way forward back into housing and into being
productive members of our society.
Te Toi Mahanah, who is a social housing provider right here in Wellington,
is a perfect example of making things work.
They've just released an economic benefit
report that showed that their social homes deliver a three to
one investment.
So this isn't just about doing the right thing.
This is also about the economic benefit of investing in
social housing
rather than seeing homeless people as a problem that needs to
be out of sight.
Finally, Kaibosh urges the committee to consider the human rights
implications of this bill. In our view, penalizing
someone for life-sustaining acts, sitting,
sleeping, shelter,
when they have no private space to do so, is the criminalization
of poverty itself.
It draws people into the justice system,
saddles
them with fines they cannot pay, and pushes them further from
housing, volunteering, and employment, not closer.
We cannot police our way out of a housing crisis.
I urge this committee to reject this bill, or at a minimum
substantially amend it so that no enforcement penalties
occur. Let's
redirect focus and funding towards housing first initiatives,
wraparound mental health support, and community outreach,
working alongside the charities already doing the heavy lifting
rather than pushing our most vulnerable out of sight.
And
we do, Suzy, have a couple of questions, starting with Dan Rosewarne and then
Camilla Belich.
Thanks for that contribution. It's much appreciated.
The Christchurch Methodist Mission raised a similar point that you made
about people, they often sleep in a well-lit and populated
areas because they're safer than parks or isolated
locations. In your view, what risks do people
face when they are pushed away from those areas, particularly women, young
people, and older rough sleepers?
Yeah, as I said, we're not an expert in this area, but in the things that
I've read,
you've nailed it. It's pushing people out to places that they
don't know,
that don't have people around, that don't have those safety nets that
they can find in more centralized locations.
Thank you.
Camilla and then Lawrence.
Thank you. Just a really excellent point that you made around the proximity of
these support services. In your experience probably in
relation to, I guess, the bigger centers, but these will apply everywhere.
Are most of those support services usually clustered
around areas where people are more likely to be
moved on for, so say, central business districts and that kind of thing?
Or how many providers would be
in more suburban or outside those areas?
Yeah, I would say the majority of our support networks are
in that central area. And it just makes it
easy to find people that are living without houses.
They are in those areas because that's where the support networks are,
and have always traditionally been.
They were set up to support those in need, and that's where they are, so that's
where they've set themselves up. Yeah.
Yeah.
Lawrence, please.
Cool. Thanks, Chair. Thank you, Suzy, and your submission.
One of the things I think that's falling on from the idea
of support service network, and one of the argument is when you
do see aggressive behaviors, for example, I guess
the question then is: what sort of wraparound service should
there be?
Because again, criminalizing may not be the solution, but what sort of wraparound
service should there be, and what are the availability of those services,
24 hours,
24/7 services?
Yeah, that's a great question you could hold for DCM later today.
But they are one of the main supporters of our homeless whanau
here in Wellington. And certainly they are
supported to an extent to look after
the people living on the street, but I'm not sure the support goes far
enough. And I would say I feel like
having spoken to them, there is also some massive
issues with mental health
there. And so, are the police the best people to be
dealing with mental health crises?
For them and for the people they
need to support, I would say, people that are trained to
support people with mental health issues are probably in a better position to do
so.
Okay, Suzy, thank you very much. That's right on time.
Thank you for your thought that you've put into that submission today.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you.
Good luck. Bye-bye.
Right, so that's the end of that part of the hearings.
But we're going to move on, members, to item four on the agenda.
It's the report of the
Attorney-General under the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act 1990 on the
Summary Offences
Amendment Bill.
We've received papers to be tabled, was the letter
from the Crown Law. So just make a note,
the instructions in that letter. And there's the hearing of
evidence now from the Crown Law, Austin Powell.
So we'll look forward to seeing Austin on screen in a moment.
Good afternoon. Can you hear me okay?
Yes, we can. That's come through fine. Welcome, Austin.
We've got your letter, and I also just note for the members who may not have
that up, that you're confined to section seven.
So you might just want to run that through just so members are aware of what you
can comment on and while you're on screen at the moment.
So, we'll leave it in your hands.
Thank you. I should first clarify, I'm not Austin.
I'm standing in for Austin today. I'm David Neild.
Well, that's
not a great start by me, but
welcome.
No, that's very understandable.
But maybe you can give some clarity around that letter. Thank you.
So Austin is in court today, so was unable to attend.
But I'm familiar with the issue. I'm a Crown counsel at Crown Law
As you probably know, Pānau supports the Attorney General in vetting
legislation for the Bill of Rights Act compliance.
As you've noted, I can only comment on matters
addressed in a Section 7 report. I can't comment on policy questions, which
confines what I can
say. If it's helpful, I'll just give a very brief summary of the Section
7 process and the vet that's been handled by the Attorney.
That would be great for all members. Yes.
So, as you'll know, the Attorney General is a very unusual position.
He is a minister and a member of Cabinet,
but he also has obligations to act independently, and one of
those is his obligation in Section 7 of the Bill of Rights Act, where
he is responsible when a government bill is introduced
for informing our Parliament if he considers that the
bill appears to be inconsistent with the rights and freedoms in the Bill of
Rights Act. Although Pānau
supports the Attorney in this obligation, the legal responsibility
for reporting sits with the Attorney,
who considers officials' advice and reaches his own conclusions.
So the section vet is the Attorney General's views.
It's important to note that the rights and freedoms in the Bill of Rights Act
absolutely can and often are limited.
Many, if not most bills, limit protected rights.
So the question often turns on whether the limits are reasonable under
Section 5 of the Bill of Rights Act.
Turning to this particular Section 7 report,
the Attorney concluded that the move-on
orders, as currently drafted, limit two
freedoms in the Bill of Rights Act, freedom of expression, although that's
only in respect of the begging aspect of the move-on
orders,
and also freedom of movement, and that's in respect of both the begging and the
rough sleeping aspects.
Turning to the Section 5 analysis, which is whether the limits are
reasonably justified, there is a four-step test.
The first two steps are whether the purpose is sufficiently important and whether
the limit is rationally connected to the purpose.
The Attorney concluded those steps were met, but he concluded that the
third step was not met. That's whether the
proposal is within a range of reasonably
rights-limiting alternatives.
And he identified three potentially less
rights-infringing
alternatives that the scope of move-on
orders could be narrower,
that the bill could include guidance for constables about what to take into
account when
considering whether to issue a move-on order.
And finally, that when someone is issued with a move-on order, that it might be
appropriate for them to be able to come back into the area for a different purpose.
For example, to go to a shop to purchase food.
So I'm happy to take any questions.
We do have a couple of questions. We'll start with Dr Laurence Yuen On,
and then followed by Carmela Belic.
Cool. Thank you so much, David, for that.
I got two questions. One of them is specifically around freedom of
expression. Looking at the Section 7 report, could you just elaborate on some
of the, I guess, the international rulings around
the interaction, this, and also in terms of the overall
UN,
the covenants or declarations around human rights? That being my first question.
My second question is, one of the things we've heard previously from another
submitter is actually around Section 12 of BORA,
potentially, which is around the right for people to
vote, and I think this is specifically in the context of what
happens if, let's say,
someone is being moved on from
a voting booth, et
cetera.
I wondered if you've actually considered some of the other scenarios in the BORA
report, because I don't see Section 12 being mentioned, for example.
Well, I'll take that second question first.
No, we haven't considered Section
12. I can't sort of elaborate on the Section 7 report.
It's not in there. It hasn't been considered by the Attorney.
I would need to go away and think about that to answer that question.
Sorry. I'm so sorry, David. The other one that's tied in Section 12 that's not in
there, Section 16 around peaceful assembly, if you wouldn't mind also. Yeah.
No, the same answer to that. I can't really elaborate on the
report.
Yes, I'd have to think about that more. Sorry.
And there's not a lot I can add about the international law that's set out,
obviously, at paragraph 14. And
the Attorney has noted that there
are different approaches internationally,
but he has concluded that
if someone is begging and they're holding a sign, for
example,
that that would engage freedom of expression, which is fairly broadly
defined. Even if you just look at the wording of the Bill of Rights Act itself, it
includes, for example, receiving information.
And I can't go beyond the cases that are in the
report itself. Sorry.
That's all good. Thank you so much.
We'll go on to Carmela, please.
Thanks, and I appreciate you're standing in for someone today as well.
But I did-- obviously, when the Attorney does do the
Section 7 report, they have to apply all of the potential Bill of
Rights rights to the particular piece of draft
legislation. So there was just a couple of things in there, and it might be that
you have the same answer, but that I
just wanted to ask about whether this was considered or not.
The Attorney in his Section 7 report has-
listed indirect discrimination in relation to employment, and I wanted
to know if there was any consideration around
age in relation to indirect discrimination,
because obviously there is a provision around age, but there's
younger people. So
this applies to children, technically children under the law.
Also, if there was consideration around
disability, which is a protected characteristic,
if there was any consideration around that being
indirectly discriminatory and also just based on the
information on the risk around ethnicity being another area of indirect
discrimination. So
would appreciate your answer on that.
But the other question that I wanted to know was,
you've specifically talked about how the Attorney General has
said that there are potential limits,
that it potentially could be too
wide, the begging provision, especially in
relation
to the rights in the Bill of Rights Act.
So is what the Attorney General is suggesting a
more limited, or would it be Bill of Rights compliant if
a more limited definition of begging was included?
Or in the Section seven report, there's suggestions
around criteria that could be put in place.
So that's a potential amendment that the attorney is suggesting to
make this compliant with the Bill of Rights.
I wouldn't want to frame it like that, because the
question that the attorney is answering is,
are there less rights
infringing alternatives? And I don't want to
go beyond that framing.
What he has said is that only the begging and the
rough sleeping
aspects of move on orders limit rights.
So if those grounds weren't part of the move on orders, if you only had
paragraphs A to D,
then you wouldn't limit any rights.
So you wouldn't even get to the section five, if that helps.
In terms of once you do limit those rights through some
version of the begging or the rough sleeping grounds, then the question
is,
are there less rights infringing measures?
And certainly at paragraph 22,
he said that he considers the scope of the begging ground is
without more too wide. And he
has made suggestions there,
but bearing in mind, at this stage, all the attorney is being asked
to do is, is it possible that there's a less--
Is this measure within a range of
reasonable
alternatives? And he said no, because the scope
could be narrower in a way that still addresses the policy.
I'm uncomfortable going into
questions around what exactly would that look like, because that's really a policy
question,
and probably the best people to answer that would be Ministry of Justice officials.
And what was your other question? Sorry. Your other question was about rights.
Just asking about applying indirect discrimination to other protected grounds like
disability, ethnicity, age.
Unfortunately, I can't go beyond the Section seven report, and that's partly
because any advice he received on it would have been from Crown Law, and of
course, that
advice would be legal advice, which,
both for privileged reasons I can't go into, but also I don't think it's probably
helpful for me to go beyond the rights that the attorney has
identified as being limited and
what he's outlining he's considered in the advice.
I'm not sure I understood the question about age.
I found that a bit tricky.
I guess it's a
policy that applies to everyone, but it might indirectly impact
those who are younger, who have fewer means and
ways that they can access support.
I'm not sure it affects everyone, does it?
Because I think it's
people who are 14 and over.
Well, that's true, but it's-
Yeah
... it might indirectly impact on those who are younger,
more. Well, that's a question that you could pose to see if it was indirectly
discriminatory.
I'd need to think about that more, I think.
Thanks.
Okay. Thank you, David. Doesn't seem to be any further
questions, so thank you for the advice that you've
been able to give there. Members, we've reached that
lunch break time. We're only three or four minutes over, so we've
done pretty well this morning. We'll be back at
1:00 with Tom Rutherford as the chair.
So we'll welcome you back at 1:00 and be back in
public. Cheers.
Thank
you.